<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./bnsample-icon.png" 
			type="Other" 
			xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" 
			xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
			xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
			
    <name>Enumerate BN</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Creates a table with all the combinations of values and the corresponding probabilities
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        Using a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayesian_network">Bayesian Network</a> which describes densities of probabilities, 
        this node generates a data table  
        with columns corresponding the variables of the BN, 
        and the content of cells being the combinations of the categories of the variables.
        
		<p>
 		Enumeration of all the nodes depends on the count of variables and of their domains. 
 		It might be very long, as its cost grows as a combination of the variables and domains sizes.
 		As a general rule of thumb, it is often better to use sampling out of a network 
 		than enumerate all its possibilities. Enumeration mostly makes sense on small networks,
 		or on networks containing many zeros in the conditional probability tables.
		</p>

		<p>
 		Enumeration is more tractable if we reduce the combinations by pruning some possibilities.
 		<ul>
 		<li>The first way to make it is not to create the rows for which probability is null. 
 		This way the algorithm will first try to compute the nodes containing many zeros, so it will 
 		quickly stop computing many combinations, and will also not spend time writing the rows into the table.</li>
 		<li>Another possibility is to define a minimal probability for a row to be added to the 
 		resulting table. In this case the algorithm will first explore nodes containing small 
 		probabilities, and stop computing the combination as soon as the probability drops below the given probability.
 		</li>
 		</ul>
 		</p>
 		
		<p>
		Please report bugs or feature demands in <a href="https://github.com/samthiriot/knime.bayesiannetworks/issues">the github page</a>.
		</p>
		</intro>
        
        <option name="skip impossible combinations">when a combination of values leads to probability 0, do not create the row (default)</option>
        <option name="skip combinations with too low probabilities">when a combination of values has a probability below epsilon, do not create the row (default)</option>
        <option name="minimal probability">lowest probability to consider. Note that large networks always lead to very small probabilities, so even 1E-50 might keep no result!</option>    

    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Bayesian network">Bayesian network</inPort>
        <!-- possibly more input ports here-->
        <outPort index="0" name="enumeration">Combinations generated from the Bayesian network</outPort>
        <!-- possibly more output ports here-->
    </ports>    
</knimeNode>
