<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./bnsample-icon.png" 
			type="Other" 
			xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" 
			xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
			xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
			
    <name>Sample From BN</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
        Using a Bayesian network which describes densities of probabilities, 
        this node generates a population of entities (data table) 
        with columns corresponding the variables of the BN.
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        Using a  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayesian_network">Bayesian network</a> which describes densities of probabilities, 
        this node generates a data table  
        with columns corresponding the variables of the BN, and the content of cells being the categories of the variables.
        
        <p>
        Three sampling methods are available:
        <ul>
        <li><b>forward sampling</b>: for each entity to generate, will start with one root of the network, sample one value; 
        continue with a next node, compute the conditional probabilities, sample one value, and so on. 
        Purely stochastic. <b>Efficient for small counts</b>. For small numbers, no guarantee that the resulting frequencies are as close as possible as probabilities.</li>
        <li><b>multinomial sampling</b>: for <tt>n</tt> entities to generate, will start with one root of the network, and then sample
        the expected frequency of this probability for <tt>n</tt> entities; then it will explore the next node, compute the conditional 
        probabilities, sample the expected frequencies for this probabilities and <tt>n2</tt> entities to sample, etc. 
        This method is more efficient when there are many entities to generate. This method preserve the probability distribution
        over multiple samples.
        It is possible to group the similar lines 
        together.</li>
        <li><b>round and sample</b>: for <tt>n</tt> entities to generate, assumes we should always be as close as possible to the proportions
        described in the probability distribution. For each node of the network, will compute the probabilities, then 
        count how many entities should be for sure generated. Then for the remaining entities, samples randomly which ones 
        are going to be sampled. This method is more efficient. This method preserves the probability distribution for one
        sample, but not for several samples (there will not be much variations between two runs)</li>
        </ul>
        </p>
        
        <p>Computing time depends on the size of the Bayesian network: size of the Conditional Probability Tables, 
        count of them. 
        The behavior is not linear thanks to caching of computations: the more lines your compute, the quicker it goes.
        If you use multinomial sampling or round and sample, and the resulting table contains mostly counts of 1, 
        then using forward sampling would be more efficient. Both these methods become efficient when they achieve 
        to create combinations by group. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
        The random numbers are generated using the <a href="https://dst.lbl.gov/ACSSoftware/colt/">Colt library</a> 
        (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colt_(libraries)">the wikipedia page</a>) published by CERN. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Go there to <a href="https://github.com/samthiriot/knime.bayesiannetworks/issues">report bugs or ask for features</a>
        </p>
        </intro>
        
        
        <option name="Samples">How many lines to sample (generate)</option>
        <option name="Seed">Enables you to freeze the Random Number Generator used to sample. 
        If you do not understand what this means, keep it unchecked so a different result is produced at every run.</option>
       
        <option name="generation method">How to sample. See earlier.</option>
        <option name="group similar rows">If several rows are similar, grouping will add a column count and indicate the count there; 
        else one row will be created for each result</option>
        <option name="use all CPUs">If checked, will detect the amount of CPU on your computer and use them for quicker sampling.</option>
        <option name="max CPU to use">Count of CPUs to use.</option>
        <option name="do not store (xp)">Sample, but do not store the results into a table. Useful only when doing benchmarks of generations methods, without having storage being part of the generation time. Keep unchecked.</option>
        
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Bayesian network">Bayesian network</inPort>
        <outPort index="0" name="sample">Samples generated from the Bayesian network</outPort>
    </ports>    
</knimeNode>
