<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./bnreader-icon.png" 
			type="Other" 
			xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.8" 
			xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
			xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.10 http://knime.org/node/v2.10.xsd">
			
    <name>Add Node to BN</name>
    
    <shortDescription>
		Adds a node to a Bayesian Network using the input table 
    </shortDescription>
    
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
        Adds a node to a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayesian_network">Bayesian Network</a> 
        using the input table which describes its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conditional_probability_table">Conditional Probability Table</a>.
        
        <p>
        The input table should only contain the content necessary for the creation of the Bayesian Network Node, that is a Conditional Probability Table.
        Columns should be in the right order. Use nodes to filter and sort columns if necessary.
        <ul>
         <li>The <b>first column</b> contains the modalities of the variable to be created. 
        The title of the column defines the <b>name of the variable</b> in the Bayesian network. 
        It should contain categorical data (string, integer...).</li>
        <li>The <b>last column</b> contains the probabilities. 
        It should be numeric, and will be normalized to be treated as probabilities.</li>
        <li>All <b>the columns inbetween</b> will be interpreted as <b>dependent variables</b>.
       	They should contain categorical data (String, integer, long...). </li>
        </ul>
		</p>
		
		<p>      
	    When the node is added to the Bayesian network, if the names of dependent variables already exist in the 
	    Bayesian network, they will be connected in the network (and the modalities should be the same).
	    Else the variable is created from scratch with an hypothesis of equiprobability. 
	    </p>
	
		<p>    
		In this first example of input table, we provide a Conditional Probability Table 
	    which defines a node <tt>p(gender)</tt> without dependent variable.
	    </p>
   	    <table>
		  <tr>
		    <th>gender</th>
		    <th>p</th>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>male</td>
		    <td>0.55</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>female</td>
		    <td>0.45</td>
		  </tr>
		</table>
		<p>
		It will be interpreted as:
   	    </p>		
	<pre>
	p( gender=male ) = 0.55
	p( gender=female ) = 0.45
	</pre>
			
		<p>    
		In this second example of input table, we provide a Conditional Probability Table 
	    which defines a node <tt>p(age|gender)</tt> which defines the variable <tt>age</tt> with dependent variable <tt>gender</tt>.
   	   	</p>
   	    <table>
		  <tr>
		    <th>age</th>
		    <th>gender</th>
		    <th>p</th>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>baby</td>
		    <td>male</td>
		    <td>12</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>teen</td>
		    <td>male</td>
		    <td>21</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>adult</td>
		    <td>male</td>
		    <td>65</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>baby</td>
		    <td>female</td>
		    <td>10</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>teen</td>
		    <td>female</td>
		    <td>17</td>
		  </tr>
		  <tr>
		    <td>adult</td>
		    <td>female</td>
		    <td>72</td>
		  </tr>		  
		</table>
		<p>
		If the input Bayesian network does not already contains a variable named <tt>gender</tt>, this variable will be created with equiprobability.
		The dependent node <tt>p(age|gender)</tt> will be defined after normalization, as follows:
		</p>
	<pre>
	p( gender )
	p( gender=male ) = 0.5
	p( gender=female ) = 0.5
	
	p( age | gender )
	p( age=baby | gender=male ) = 0.12244897959183673
	p( age=baby | gender=female ) = 0.10101010101010101
	p( age=teen | gender=male ) = 0.21428571428571427
	p( age=teen | gender=female ) = 0.1717171717171717
	p( age=adult | gender=male ) = 0.6632653061224489
	p( age=adult | gender=female ) = 0.7272727272727273
	</pre>

		<p>
		Please report bugs or feature demands in <a href="https://github.com/samthiriot/knime.bayesiannetworks/issues">the github page</a>.
		</p>
		
	    </intro>
	    
        
        <option name="accept multiple occurences">If checked, the same combinations might be provided several times. 
        				Uncheck it if the table is the result of a group by, should be false. </option>
       
    </fullDescription>
    
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Bayesian network">Bayesian network to modify</inPort>
        <inPort index="1" name="table">data table containing the probabilities</inPort>
        
        <outPort index="0" name="Bayesian network">Bayesian network with the additional node</outPort>
        
    </ports>
    
    
</knimeNode>